<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Iesuit, and the monk: or, The serpent, and the dragon: or, Profession, and practice. Being a sermon preached on the fifth of November, 1656. / By Richard Carpenter.</title>
            <author>Carpenter, Richard, d. 1670?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80534</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C622</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E897_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206691</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865807</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865807</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118058</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80534)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118058)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 135:E897[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Iesuit, and the monk: or, The serpent, and the dragon: or, Profession, and practice. Being a sermon preached on the fifth of November, 1656. / By Richard Carpenter.</title>
                  <author>Carpenter, Richard, d. 1670?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Francis Leach,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb: 22".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs IV, 14 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118058:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE IESUIT, AND THE MONK: OR, THE <hi>Serpent,</hi> and the <hi>Dragon:</hi> OR, <hi>Profeſsion,</hi> and <hi>Practice.</hi> Being a Sermon Preached on the fifth of <hi>November,</hi> 1656.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Richard Carpenter.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Job 8. 13.</bibl>
               <p>The Hypocrites Hope ſhall periſh.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>St. Bern. de Grat. &amp; lib. Arb.</bibl>
               <p>Utitur Deus Creaturâ rationali, ſed malevolâ, ut Virgâ, quam Correcto Filio, Pater in Ignem, tanquam Sarmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum inutile, abjicit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God uſes a reaſonable Creature, being malevolous, <hi>(and ſeeking the Deſtruction of others)</hi> as a Rod, which, the Child being Corrected <hi>(or terrified) by what line ſoever his <hi>Childſhip</hi> is deſcended to him,</hi> the Father throws into the fire as unprofitable.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Francis Leach,</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118058:2"/>
            <head>To all Worthy Perſons, that are <hi>pure-intention'd,</hi> and have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Thoughts, and Hearts which abominate <hi>Fraud, Fallacy, Falſhood, Lying, Slandering,</hi> yea all kinds of <hi>Impoſture</hi> and <hi>Wickedneſs,</hi> eſpecially ſuch as ſtinks of a <hi>Powder-Plot.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Oble Souls, who and where ſoever ye are, Forgive me, if I preſume upon your ſoftneſs, and humbly implore the Honour of your Patronage. We read in the old <hi>Monuments,</hi> of <hi>Eunomius,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Photius in Ep. ad Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annem Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricium.</note> that, he playing upon his Harp in a ſolemn trial of Skill, and a String failing him, a Graſhopper preſently ſate upon his Harp, and ſo <hi>ſymmetrically</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted with the Muſick, that it perfectly ſupplyed the Work of the broken String; and moreover was in the Cauſe, that <hi>Eunomius</hi> went Conquerour. I may perhaps, in this fervorous Conteſt, with a quick and chearfull stroke, break a String; the String of Health, or Life: But more excellent Graſhoppers with Harps in their Breſts, (it is the Phraſe of <hi>St. Gregory Nazianzen;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">S. Greg. Naz. Orat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 34.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>Who gives to the Graſhopper, the Harp in its Breſt?</hi>) than you Selves, I deſire not to have in view, for the perfect ſupplyance of the Muſick.</p>
            <p>Ye ſtate your Quarrel according to the <hi>Poſition</hi> of your Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences: which I likewiſe do. But I am principally gaſhed, and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the <hi>fruits</hi> of <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and <hi>Monks;</hi> becauſe they more <hi>ſtrike the Senſe;</hi> and chiefly, becauſe our bleſſed Saviour is ſo very much preſſing on that part. <note place="margin">Mat. 7. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Ye ſhall know them by their fruits: Doe men gather grapes of thorns, or figs of thiſtles?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">v. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Even ſo every good Tree bringeth forth good fruit: but a corrupt Tree bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth evil fruit.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">v. 18.</note> 
               <hi>A good Tree cannot bring forth evil fruit: neither can a corrupt Tree bring forth good fruit.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">v. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Every Tree that bringeth not forth good fruit, is hewen down, and caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fire.</hi> It returns in the ſhape of a <hi>Concluſion,</hi> proved to the height of <hi>Diſcourſe:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">v. 20.</note> 
               <hi>Wherefore by their fruits ye ſhall know them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Agreeably to my light and ſight the <hi>Monks</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits</hi> ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le and write their Vices, Vertues; as that impure Perſon, who called his Whores by the Names of the <hi>Muſes;</hi> or like the Painter, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred the Picture of his lewd Mistreſs, under the Name of the <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Virgin,</hi> that it might be honour'd.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:118058:3"/>
            <p>Our Saviour being hungry, after long fasting, <note place="margin">Matt. 4. 3.</note> the <hi>Devil</hi> rejects him to <hi>Stones</hi> in the place of Bread. Again, he being hungry, <note place="margin">Matt. 21. 19.</note> the <hi>Fig-tree</hi> offers him nothing but leafs. And when at the laſt, <note place="margin">Io. 19. 28, 29.</note> he cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Croſſe, <hi>I thirſt,</hi> he was relieved by the <hi>Jews</hi> only with <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar.</hi> I hope I long ago learned to <note place="margin">Matt. 5. 6.</note> 
               <hi>hunger and thirſt after Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs.</hi> But when I thought to have been plentifully <hi>filled,</hi> the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> and <hi>Monks</hi> did not at any Time ſet any Thing before me, but Stones, Leafs, Vinegar; or, as they are of the hoggiſh kind, <hi>Husks:</hi> that is, <hi>Fraud, Fallacy, Falſhood, Lying, Slandering, Impoſture, Wickedneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>Chymiſtry,</hi> the <hi>Tranſmutations</hi> of Things are ſuperlatively ſtrange, if we attempt the reduction of them to nothing. I know that your <hi>Prolepſis,</hi> will eaſily prevent my <hi>Interpretation.</hi> Howſoever the <hi>Lot</hi> falls, My <hi>Spiritual Appetire</hi> lies not in my Ears; and I cannot be fed with gawdy Words, and <hi>Pious Orations</hi> concerning Heaven: I must behold Heaven practiſed.</p>
            <p>This Sermon had been <hi>nothing but a Voice,</hi> though the <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> were the Auditors; had not impudent Slander extorted it from me, and bound it over to the Preſs. Now therefore, as the <hi>Monks</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits</hi> are, in our <hi>Saviour's dialect,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7. 16.</note> 
               <hi>thiſtles</hi> and <hi>thorns,</hi> I ſhall be <hi>as Thorns in their ſides;</hi> and endeavour by all means poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and imaginable, to fetch the <hi>Geraſen Hog,</hi> and the <hi>dirty De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> out of their mouths, that <hi>wallows in</hi> all <hi>the mire,</hi> and impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Fraud, Fallacy, Falſhood, &amp;c. and will be there <hi>wallowing,</hi> until it <hi>runs violently down a ſteep place into the Sea, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes in the waters.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 8. 32.</note> Had they been ſoul'd with the Spirit of the <hi>Primitive Saints,</hi> they had been <hi>rapted</hi> to a <hi>Sublime Courſe,</hi> as <hi>reaſonably</hi> and <hi>graciouſly</hi> caught thereunto by many <hi>ſublime Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations.</hi> But theſe are Swine, and <hi>Lovers of Pleaſure,</hi> and of their Bellies, more than Lovers of God. And when they call me to it by their new <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncivilities, I will plainly ſhew you, as ye view in the Picture of the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> or <hi>Monk</hi> here, the very <hi>Hog-Devil</hi> in their Teeth, and at the end of their Tongues; and lay down the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons before your Eyes, why I charge the <hi>Monks</hi> ſo highly, and why they are ſo monſtrous in my Glaſs. I will not at preſent, farther ſoil and defile my ſelf with touching theſe <hi>unclean Beaſts:</hi> But humbly remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours religiouſly-devoted, and to be commanded by you all. <hi>R. Carpenter.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118058:3"/>
            <head>The <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> and the <hi>Monk,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N holy Scripture there occurr <hi>Apparitions of Angels.</hi> Angels, that they may ſuit with the Condition of Men, who are bodily, and to whom they appear, muſt aſſume Bodies.</p>
               <p>I obſerve: When Angels aſſume Bodies, that they may perform God's Commands, and converſe with us here upon Earth, they never aſſume <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of Fire.</hi> (If a Spirit attempts to make a <hi>Compact,</hi> he is a Devil; if he takes a <hi>Body of fire,</hi> he is a Devil: they are two notable <hi>Marks</hi> of a <hi>Diabolical Apparition.</hi>) The great <hi>Aquinas</hi> adminiſters the Reaſon; <note place="margin">D. Tho. p. 1. q. 51. art. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Becauſe, if they ſhould take Bodies of fire,</hi> comburerent ea quae contingerent, <hi>they would then ſet on fire all they ſhould touch.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Angel's Buſineſs, is not to be an Incendiary, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame and fire all where he comes; but <hi>proportionably</hi> and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>attemper</hi> himſelf to our bodily and <hi>qualified Condition,</hi> in the performance of God's holy Will and Commands.</p>
               <p>Our Prieſts from beyond the <hi>Alpes,</hi> boldly ſtile themſelves <hi>Angels;</hi> becauſe Angelus eſt Nomen Officii, <hi>Angel is the Name of their Office.</hi> They derive this their honourary Title, chiefly from the <hi>Prophet</hi> who is named <hi>Angel,</hi> and whom <hi>Origen</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thought to have been an Angel; <note place="margin">Ita S. Hier. in Prooem. ad Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiam.</note> the <hi>Prophet Malachy.</hi> Who ſpeaks thus, ch. 2. v. 7. Labia enim Sacerdotis cuſtodier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Scientiam, et legem requirent ex ore ejus: quia Angelus Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini Exercituum eſt. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> repeats it after this manner, <hi>For the Prieſts lips ſhould keep knowledge, and they ſhould ſeek the law at his mouth: for he is the Meſſenger of the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Sept.</note> In the <hi>Greek</hi> it is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the Angel of the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> And in this ſenſe Chriſt ſaith of <hi>John the Baptiſt,</hi> Mat. 11. 10. <hi>Behold I ſend my Meſſenger.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Evang. Graec.</note> The <hi>Greek</hi> alloweth, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>Behold, I ſend and commiſsionate my Angel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I believe, It is the hearty Wiſh of all Chriſtian People, that theſe <hi>Italian Angels</hi> would not come to us in <hi>Bodies of Fire,</hi> and burn all as they go.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="sermon">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:118058:4"/>
               <head>My Text greets you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Prov. 4. 14. in the end.</bibl>
                     <p>Goe not in the way of Evil Men.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe <hi>Vulgar Edition</hi> delivers it, <note place="margin">Edit. Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat.</note> Nec tibi placeat malorum Via: <hi>Neither let the way of evil men pleaſe thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Reading is more reſtrictive; and indeed narrows the ſenſe, and binds it even to the denial of all delight, pleaſure, or complacence <hi>in the ways of evil men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Context in the <hi>Latine Bible,</hi> eſpecially touched with the <hi>Original,</hi> gives us to know what manner of <hi>Evil men</hi> theſe are, and that they have <hi>ſulphureous hearts,</hi> and that their holy work is to ſupplant and deſtroy Princes.</p>
               <p>The Text is a <hi>negative Exhortation,</hi> moving us to decline the crooked way and evil example of ſuch profane men as are <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planters</hi> of their Brethren.</p>
               <p>We muſt not goe in this way, becauſe it is <hi>the way of evil men:</hi> that is to ſay, it is not the way of the <hi>Saints</hi> and Servants of God, to which we are called.</p>
               <p>Aſſuredly <hi>Jacob</hi> was a <hi>Saint of God,</hi> and the ſame, a <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planter</hi> of his Brother: But he <hi>ſupplanted</hi> him irrationally, that is, when he had not as yet the uſe and <hi>exerciſe of Reaſon;</hi> and he pre-occupied his Brothers Bleſſing, inſtructed by his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who now acted according to the Regulation of a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Principle: and all this was myſterious, and deſigned for the ſignification of <hi>Things</hi> afterwards to come, by him who only is able to make <hi>Things foreſignifie Things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the two Brethren now growing to ſome ripeneſs of age, are briefly characteriz'd, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25. 27. <hi>And the Boyes grew; and</hi> Eſau <hi>was a cunning Hunter, a man of the field, and</hi> Jacob <hi>was a plain man dwelling in Tents.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Codex Vulg Cod..</note> The <hi>Latine</hi> ſayes, Vir ſimplex, <hi>a ſimple man.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Hebr.</note> The word in the <hi>Hebrew Baſis</hi> is <hi>Tam:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Sept.</note> which the <hi>Septuagint</hi> render, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>not feigned, or daubed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver;</hi> that is, exempt of guile and fraud. <note place="margin">Sym.</note> 
                  <hi>Symmachus</hi> reads <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>without fault,</hi> or <hi>blemiſh, irreprehenſible.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Aq.</note> 
                  <hi>Aquila</hi> gives <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a plain man, that had nothing of duplicity in him.</hi> Where <hi>Simplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> it not <hi>oppoſed</hi> to <hi>Prudence,</hi> but to <hi>Craft</hi> and <hi>Falſehood.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:118058:4"/>
               <p>The bottom-Truth is: The <hi>Hebrew Tam</hi> ariſes from the <hi>Root Tamam,</hi> which ſignifies to <hi>perfect</hi> or <hi>conſummate;</hi> and therefore ſpeaks <hi>Jacob</hi> to have been a man of a right and good way, of an innocent work, and of a <hi>perfect life,</hi> yea, <hi>a plain man, dwelling in Tents;</hi> that is, continually meditating upon the brevity and vanity of this life, according to which inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation it is written of our Saviour Chriſt, <hi>Jo.</hi> 1. 14. <hi>And the Word was made fleſh, and dwelt among us.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Text Graec.</note> Where the <hi>Greek</hi> affixeth; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>And the Word was made fleſh, and pitched his Tent or Tabernacle among us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beloved, ye have ſeen holy <hi>Jacob;</hi> and ye have ſeen him differenced from his Brother <hi>Eſau.</hi> I have ſeen much of <hi>Eſau,</hi> and ſomewhat of <hi>Jacob</hi> in the world. In all the gleanings of my <hi>Experience</hi> gathered from the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> I cannot find with a Candle (I had almoſt ſaid) one Prieſt (with whom I have mingled near acquaintance, commerce and converſation) that hath not (give me leave to ſpeak at large; for the <hi>Things</hi> are beyond ordinary limit and compaſs) <hi>a thouſand</hi> Eſaus <hi>in him, and more than a million of our common and quotidian Mountebanks and Jugglars.</hi> (They are <hi>Cunning Hunters</hi> after Money, Books, Apparel, Goods, Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and Gifts out of the Country; of all which in their kinds the good Monks have cheated me; having then in a manner, blown me up, though not with Powder. And therefore their continual, and moſt ready <hi>Profeſſion</hi> is, that <hi>they are poor.</hi>) And whither will not the bold and preſumptuous attempts of ſuch high-ſoaring people aſcend? This <hi>Diabolical Fraud, Falſhood, Cunning,</hi> is the moſt unhappy Mother of all damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble miſchief.</p>
               <p>Now God hath moreover declared, that he converſeth chiefly, that is, intimately, and familiarly, with <hi>ſimple</hi> Hearts. As <hi>Prov.</hi> 3. 32. <hi>For the froward is abomination to the Lord: but his Secret is with the Righteous.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Edit. Vulg.</note> The <hi>Vulgar Latine</hi> ſpeaks it more plainly: Quia abominatio Domini eſt omnis illuſor, &amp; cum ſimplicibus Sermocinatio ejus. <hi>For God abominates every Mocker and Deceiver, and his Communication is with the ſimple.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Text. Hebr.</note> It lies couch'd in the <hi>Hebrew, His Secret is with the right.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Aben Ezra in hunc lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> To the which <hi>Aben Ezra</hi> contributes his reaſon. <hi>Becauſe God communicates his Counſels and Secrets unto thoſe who are right of Heart.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Chald. Paraphr.</note> And therefore the <hi>Chaldee</hi> diggs it up: Cum rectis
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118058:5"/> Colloquium ejus, <hi>He talks privately, and entertains the ſweet Colloquies of Love, with ſuch as are ſimple, right and candid,</hi> not with ſuch, who, geſtant ſub pectore Vulpem, who <hi>carry</hi> a whole kennel of Foxes, or <hi>a Fox in their Breſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the Reaſon, why God admits not of any friendly and familiar Converſation with Deceivers, Deſtroyers, and ſuch as have a <hi>Powder-mill</hi> in their brains, is, becauſe all ſuch are extracted from the <hi>ſeed of the old Serpent,</hi> and are the <hi>Children of Cain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As ſoon as we hear of <hi>the Serpent</hi> in holy Scripture, we hear likewiſe of his <hi>Subtilty,</hi> and that he is pragmatical, buſie, yea full of violent action and miſchief. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 1. <hi>Now the Serpent was more ſubtle than any beaſt of the field.</hi> He was, Doctor Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilis, <hi>a Subtle Doctor.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Edit. Latina.</note> The <hi>Latine</hi> unſheaths it: Sed &amp; Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens erat callidior cunctis animantibus terrae, <hi>more crafty,</hi> that is (ſay ſome, not I) <hi>more Jeſuitical, more Monkiſh.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Aq.</note> 
                  <hi>Aquila</hi> goes to the root, and affords <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>more pragmatical,</hi> more acting, moving, reſtleſſe, and more fire-like; more ready for every work and ſhape, whereby he may deceive; yea, ready to perform, if it were poſſible, all works at once, that he might delude all mankind in one manifold performance.</p>
               <p>The holy Apoſtle imitates <hi>Aquila,</hi> and ſanctifies his Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this parricular, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 3. <hi>But I fear, leſt by any means, as the Serpent beguiled</hi> Eve <hi>through his ſubtilty, ſo your minds ſhould be corrupted from the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt.</hi> For, <hi>through his ſubtilty,</hi> the <hi>Greek</hi> aſſumes <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>in his craft, when he takes all ſhapes, and works all things to comply with his deteſtable and horrible Ends.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Gather your thoughts together now, and, I pray, note with me; that here in the beginning of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> the firſt Book of Holy Scripture, the beaſt into which the Devil entred, hath his Name, à Serpendo, <hi>from creeping.</hi> He was but a <hi>creep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beaſt</hi> when he firſt began to plot againſt us. I utter the words of my Soul, Heart, and Spirit: The <hi>Jeſuites</hi> and <hi>Monks,</hi> (if I may religiouſly ſay ſo) have egregiouſly out-done him, and gone exceſſively beyond all that he did or could have done when he was a <hi>Creeper.</hi> Now it is plain, that the <hi>Serpent,</hi> the <hi>Creeper,</hi> is in length of time grown into a <hi>Dragon;</hi> ſuch we find him in the laſt Book of Scripture the <hi>Revelation, Chap.</hi> 7. 12. <hi>And there was War in Heaven,</hi> Michael <hi>and his Angels fought
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118058:5"/> against the Dragon, and the Dragon fought, and his Angels.</hi> Had not the <hi>Dragon</hi> been a Spirit, and his Enemy <hi>Michael,</hi> a Spirit, ye had heard here perhaps, in the <hi>introit</hi> of the laſt Times, of the firſt <hi>Powder-Plot.</hi> But, however the Devil is grown from a <hi>Creeping Serpent to a Flying Dragon,</hi> think not, I beſeech you (I am heartily ſorry that I have cauſe to ſay it) that the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> and the <hi>Monk</hi> fly far behind him.</p>
               <p>Indeed, and in truth, A Man skill'd in the Motions, Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Actions, Tranſactions, and Overtures of <hi>Rome,</hi> would have reaſonably thought, that, if there were any pure and ſilken threads of <hi>true Chriſtian ſincerity &amp; ſimplicity</hi> interweav'd into the Practice of the Church, they would have been found amongſt the <hi>Benedictine Monks;</hi> theſe having been the moſt antient order, and the moſt Sun-beam'd from Chriſt, as the moſt near to him. And I grant there are apparently ſuch amongſt the Religious of other Nations.</p>
               <p>But caſting aſide all the vain <hi>Follies</hi> and <hi>Falſhoods of Love,</hi> with which, I humbly confeſs I have been captivated and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chained; (for, <hi>extravagant Love,</hi> and <hi>Hatred,</hi> are alwayes er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous, and never ſound and piercing in their judgements) I declare upon my <hi>Chriſtian Word,</hi> our <hi>Engliſh Monks,</hi> who in the flouriſhing days of an <hi>old Monk, the Behemoth of humane Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy</hi> (for whoſe Aſhes I have yet ſo much Reverence, as to conceal his name, though, I beleeve, the Chronicling of his notable Actions would yeeld a great acceſs to the knowledge of <hi>Despotical Dominion</hi>) expended no time upon me, to <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> and prepare me for <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> but much to perſwade me, that the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> are the grand Abuſers of Mankind, and the mighty Plot-Maſters of the world; are now themſelves, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that the Devil is grown from a <hi>Serpent</hi> to a <hi>Dragon,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, (I will hold my Peace, but I was in the way to ſay) De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers and Impoſtors beyond a <hi>Parallel,</hi> and beyond a <hi>Rival.</hi> (And to adde) never any Dancer on the Ropes, educated his <hi>tumbling Boy;</hi> never any vile man tutor'd his <hi>Ape,</hi> to ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtrange tricks, and wondrous Faces, as theſe <hi>tumbling</hi> and <hi>Apiſh Monks</hi> are apted to, and exactly taught, when they are furniſh'd out, and manumiſed into this Nation from their <hi>Monasteries.</hi> But not a word of this.</p>
               <p>Many put it upon the queſtion, What kind of <hi>Serpent</hi> it was, into which the Devil entred. <note place="margin">Eugub.</note> 
                  <hi>Eugubinus</hi> thinks it to have been
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118058:6"/> a <hi>Baſilisk;</hi> becauſe he is the King of <hi>Serpents.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Perer. Camar. in cap. 3. Gen.</note> 
                  <hi>Pererius,</hi> that it was a <hi>Serpent</hi> called <hi>Scytales;</hi> becauſe the back thereof is vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly coloured. <note place="margin">Martinus del Rio, Diſq. Mag.</note> 
                  <hi>Martinus del Rio,</hi> a <hi>Viper. Camara,</hi> a <hi>common Snake.</hi> Others think otherwiſe: and when we have all thought, we have but thought, and can but think.</p>
               <p>I would verily believe, if I durſt, that it was a <hi>Serpent</hi> moſt fitly choſen, as having certain ſubtil poſtures, motions, and tumblings, that our young <hi>Monks</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits</hi> now uſe. My Reaſon is, The Devil had it in his comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nds from God, that he ſhould not aſſume a ſhape, but one moſt ſhewing his nature; to the end, <hi>Eve</hi> might thereby be advertiſed. <note place="margin">S. Aug. lib. de Geneſ. ad literam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cap. 3.</note> For as St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> divinely admoniſhes, Had the Work been referred to the arbitriment of the Devil, he would have rather covered his treachery (let me not ſay) his <hi>Jeſuitiſm,</hi> his <hi>Monkiſhneſs,</hi> under the ſweet ſhape of a <hi>Lamb</hi> or <hi>Pigeon,</hi> as often times the old <hi>Monks</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits</hi> do. Queſtionleſs, It was a <hi>Serpent</hi> that could move, turn, wind all manner of ways; and had (Men ſay ſo, but they ſpeak as they pleaſe) part of the motions, windings, turnings, returnings, and overturnings of <hi>bleſſed Father Garnet,</hi> when he was religiouſly inſtructing his godly Ghoſtly Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in Confeſſion, and ſub ſacro Sigillo, <hi>under the ſacred Seal,</hi> to blow up the Parliament Houſe: and moreover, had (it is not I that ſay it, but another out of the clouds) part of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and mutations of our old <hi>Monk</hi> and <hi>Behemoth,</hi> when he was inſtilling, in his <hi>cloſe</hi> and <hi>private Chamber,</hi> his <hi>black Art</hi> of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy into his <hi>Novices.</hi> But the <hi>Dragon</hi> was the compleat and maſter-Workman<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; he that poliſhed their high Performances.</p>
               <p>And that theſe are <hi>the children of Cain,</hi> all <hi>the children of Abel</hi> eaſily believe, Gen. 4. 8. <hi>Cain roſe up againſt Abel his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſlew him.</hi> Theſe <hi>roſe up againſt</hi> many thouſand Fathers and Brethren, and would have ſlain them, and given them over to a moſt horrible Death. They had a moſt pregnant and <hi>effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Will</hi> to it, and the <hi>Effect</hi> was not wanting on their part. They did not impede it, but concurred to the production of it, with the laſt dram of their Power. <hi>Cain</hi> was in the Cauſe, that his Brother <hi>Abel</hi> became <hi>Hebel, Vanity;</hi> and they would have turned all theſe their Fathers (the <hi>Fathers of their Country</hi>) and Brethren, into Vain ſmoke.</p>
               <p>A man is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a little Houſe. Wherefore the <hi>Hebrews</hi> call a Son <hi>Ben,</hi> quaſi Domum, <hi>as it were a Houſe,</hi> quam <hi>bana</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:118058:6"/> that is, which the Father hath built. How many fair Houſes of Fleſh, had the Fathers of the Perſons then deſigned for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, richly built and educated, which our baſe <hi>Children of the Serpent</hi> and of <hi>Cain,</hi> would have moſt ſuddenly and moſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly deſtroyed? <hi>King, Prince, Biſhops, Nobility, Gentry,</hi> and thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of innocent and ignorant people near to the Place, in the heat of their other Thoughts, ſhould have been fir'd and torn without a grain of Mercy.</p>
               <p>Let me tell thee, O thou <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> or, O thou <hi>Monk,</hi> (ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Power offended at thee, ſpeaks this by me) that now out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acteſt the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> in all the high and airie motions of tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Villany: the Devil could not have raiſed the duſt of his Body to this <hi>Plot,</hi> had he ſtood a <hi>Serpent;</hi> he could not, until he came, through all the Degrees and Aſcents of his <hi>Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> to ſwell into a <hi>Dragon;</hi> and until the worſt of times offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red you for his Inſtruments.</p>
               <p>Some curiouſly enquire, eſpecially of the <hi>Jewiſh Rabbins;</hi> what <hi>Sign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> it was which God ſet upon <hi>Cain,</hi> anſwerably to Scripture, Gen. 14. 15. <hi>And the Lord ſet a mark upon Cain, leſt any finding him ſhould kill him.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rabbini.</note> Some fancied this <hi>Mark</hi> or <hi>Sign</hi> to have been <hi>a moſt horrid yelling and crying;</hi> Some, <hi>a gastly Countenance, accompanied with fury;</hi> Some, <hi>a Wandriug flight;</hi> Others, <hi>a continual trembling of his Bodie;</hi> Others, a <hi>Mark impreſſed on his forehead, as with a hot iron:</hi> and thus on.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Cain's Mark</hi> of a <hi>Jeſuit</hi> or <hi>Monk,</hi> (when I ſpeak thus of the laſt of theſe, I ſpeak unwillingly) is a Face figuring it ſelf into all the Shapes of a nimble Fancy, and a Body that crout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, cringes, and winds any way, every way, all waies, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, when a Plot's upon the anvile, or, when there is <hi>Odor lucri,</hi> any ſent of gain; or, of a good Dinner.</p>
               <p>This Way, as it was not the Way of the <hi>Saints of God,</hi> but of the <hi>Serpent,</hi> and of <hi>Cain:</hi> ſo was it not the Way of the <hi>Prince of Saints, Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> And firſt, becauſe when he came into the World, as delegated by his Father to direct the World in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>good Way,</hi> his <hi>Forerunner</hi> cried out, <hi>John</hi> 3. 3. <hi>Prepare ye the way of the Lord, make his paths ſtreight.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Editio La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina.</note> The <hi>Latin</hi> inſerts, Rectas facite ſemitas ejus: <hi>make his paths right.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Text. Grae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> The <hi>Greek word</hi> is, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>right</hi> or <hi>plain.</hi> Secondly, Chriſt made his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the World, by a ſmall and ſimple Herd of poor and plain Diſciples. Thirdly, His Conqueſt was not effected by the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118058:7"/> ſhedding of other mens Bloud, but by the patient ſuffering of his own to be ſhed.</p>
               <p>In the four <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> (joyn to them the <hi>Acts of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles,</hi>) where have ye the leaſt apparition, glimpſe, or ſhadow of a <hi>Powder-plot?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is chronicled of Chriſt, Philip. 2. 8. <hi>He humbled himſelf, and became obedient unto death, even the death of the Croſs.</hi> And to this he compoſes and conforms his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> Lu. 9. 23. <hi>And he ſaid to them all, If any man will come after me, let him deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and take up his Croſs daily, and follow me.</hi> And if ye will ſearch into his very bowels, come to the 15 Chap. of St. <hi>Matth.</hi> v. 32. <hi>Then Jeſus called his Diſciples unto him, and ſaid, I have compaſſion on the multitude.</hi> He had compaſſion on the People, being hungry both in Body and Spirit: and theſe our Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners from <hi>Hell,</hi> would, that the People ſhould never have eat more, nor have ever thriv'd more in <hi>Spirit</hi> or <hi>Body.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Text. Grae.</note> The <hi>Greek</hi> propoſes it, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, <hi>I am mov'd with a great motion of affection and bowels towards the People.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Vatabl.</note> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Vatablus</hi> offers, Intimè miſeret me turbae, <hi>I have inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and in my very bowels, compaſſion towards the People.</hi> And hither ſteers the Exhortation of the <hi>Apostle,</hi> Coloſſ. 3: 12. <hi>Put on therefore (as the elect of God, holy and beloved)</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>bowels of mercies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here, <hi>Beloved,</hi> I am in the way to ſet before you, that this Way is no way anſwerable to their own <hi>Profeſsion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is a Book newly publiſhed, and lately written by a Prieſt, (I could name him to you, but I am not yet come ſo far as to name Perſons,) wherein he divides the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which is of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>fundamental,</hi> from the <hi>Opinions</hi> and various Out-walkings of the <hi>Schools.</hi> He had rendred himſelf more ingenuous, had he divided with an even hand betwixt the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice</hi> of the ſame Church. But it is probable, that Bleſſed Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity will devolve this Work upon me, and I ſhall diſpatch it with as much haſte and fidelitie as I can.</p>
               <p>As for the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the preſent time, it ſhall be ſufficient to ſhew, that this abominable way is much out of the way of their own hypocritical <hi>Profeſsion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Jeſuit</hi> and the <hi>Monk,</hi> are the Perſons I arraign: the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit,</hi> as the moſt malicious Author and <hi>Plotter</hi> of the Gunpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-Treaſon;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118058:7"/> and the <hi>Monk,</hi> (when I think of the <hi>Primitive Saints abstracted from the world,</hi> I ſigh, and am loth to ſpeak; but we are now in a lower <hi>Orb;</hi>) as one that hath of late years, put off all honeſty as a Garment, and come up to all the nimble motions of the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> in Falſhood and Perfidiouſneſs; yea gone before him, left him behind, and loſt him.</p>
               <p>Ye two, <hi>Jeſuit</hi> and <hi>Monk,</hi> (did ye not hear me ſigh?) can not be ignorant, but that I abundantly know you. And your own hearts, know with me, that neither the <hi>Indies,</hi> nor the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions of the Great Turk,</hi> nor the rugged and ragged skirts of the <hi>Arabian Deſerts,</hi> nor any other <hi>wild place</hi> of the World, where God is not known, can produce two ſuch high-flown and ſublimated <hi>Men-Dragons</hi> as your ſelves: and I ſhall prove it by your <hi>profeſsing</hi> as <hi>Men,</hi> and your <hi>performing</hi> as <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, ye <hi>profeſs</hi> as ſoon as ever ye are born into the World, that your Converſation ſhall be <hi>white,</hi> direct, ſimple, and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. For this very purpoſe, ye have put upon you in your Baptiſm, a <hi>little white linnen garment;</hi> in the which your <hi>Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptores implicitly promiſe</hi> for you, a plain, juſt, and innocent Life. <note place="margin">S. Aug. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> 157. de Temp<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> Ye call St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> to witnes in this Matter, preaching on the <hi>Octave</hi> of the <hi>Paſch,</hi> which is, with you, <hi>Dominica in Albis,</hi> the Sunday wherein all newly baptized did appear in their <hi>white,</hi> that they might appear outwardly no more in it. Hodiè Neophytorum habitus commutatur, ita tamen, ut Candor qui de habitu deponitur, ſempèr in Corde teneatur; <hi>This day the Habit of the Neophyts,</hi> (that is, of the <hi>new plants</hi> lately bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed,) <hi>is changed; yet ſo, that the whiteneſs of the Garment is tetai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the mind or heart; which is afterwards to be manifeſted in</hi> their <hi>practice.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iobius a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Photi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, Cod. 222.</note> 
                  <hi>Jobius</hi> in <hi>Photius,</hi> diſcovers the manner of it; Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didum amiculum gerebatur ſeptem dies à baptizato, <hi>The white garment was worn ſeven daies of him that was baptized,</hi> that is, from <hi>Eaſter-day,</hi> to <hi>Dominica in Albis,</hi> being the <hi>Sunday</hi> that next follows and waits upon <hi>Eaſter-Sunday.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">S. Dionyſ. Areop. de Eccl. Hier. cap. de Baptiſmo.</note> To make this ſtrong, ye go back as far as <hi>Dionyſius Areopagita,</hi> the learned Diſciple of St. <hi>Paul.</hi> Ye contend, that the <hi>white garment,</hi> not only ſignifies your <hi>whiteneſs</hi> of Soul after Baptiſm, but alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to your future <hi>whiteneſs</hi> of manners; and moreover, that your <hi>whiteneſs</hi> of manners hath <hi>anagogical reference</hi> to the <hi>white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of the robes worn in Glory: according to St. <hi>John</hi> in the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118058:8"/> Revel. 3. 4. <hi>They ſhall walk with me in white, for they are worthy;</hi> and v. 5. <hi>He that overcometh; the ſame ſhall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lothed in white rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I pray now, How doth your <hi>white Garment</hi> in Baptiſm, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the moſt <hi>Palpable darkneſs</hi> and hideous <hi>blackneſs of the Powder-plot,</hi> and with all your other execrable Actions, Jugglings, Conveyances? And, Are ye of thoſe that ſhall wear <hi>white raiment</hi> in Heaven? Had a man been indued with the Spirit of Prophecie, <hi>reſpectively unto the futurition of your Actions,</hi> and had likewiſe been preſent at your wearing of the <hi>white Dreſs</hi> in Baptiſm, he might have happily declar'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Lye in white,</hi> or the <hi>lye of the white Garment,</hi> and have ſaid, Theſe little <hi>white ones</hi> will deny their <hi>white</hi> in their <hi>black lives,</hi> and attempt to deſtroy the top and flower of their own Country with a curſed <hi>Powder-plot.</hi> O moſt Hypocritical Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion! O moſt Diabolical Practice!</p>
               <p>Secondly ye profeſs, that as ye aſcend in years, ye aſcend in Vertue. Then preſently we hear of the fifteen <hi>Gradual Pſalms,</hi> and of the Prieſts aſcending the fifteen ſtairs of the Court, when they ſang them lowder and lowder, as the Lark: <note place="margin">R. David Kimchi in Pſ. 119.</note> and <hi>R. David Chimchi</hi> is brought forth with his <hi>Records.</hi> Ye make Scripture yours in this affair, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84. 5. <hi>Bleſſed is the man whoſe ſtrength is in thee: in whoſe heart are the ways of them.</hi> The <hi>Latine</hi> is more open: Beatus vir, cujus eſt auxilium abs te: aſcenſiones in corde ſuo diſpoſuit. <hi>Bleſſed is the man whoſe help is from thee: he hath diſpoſed aſcenſions in his heart.</hi> It falls in opportunely, <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>They go from ſtrength to ſtrength.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Edit. Lat.</note> In the <hi>Latin,</hi> Ibunt de virtute in virtutem, <hi>They ſhall goe from vertue to vertue.</hi> The <hi>Hebrew</hi> hath under ground, <hi>from Army to Army.</hi> The <hi>Targ.</hi> admitteth, <hi>from one School to another. Dionyſius</hi> is called to the vogue, who requires in the <hi>Perfect way of Chriſtian Piety,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſacred Aſcenſions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tell me, I humbly pray, Have ye aſcended by theſe <hi>holy Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſions,</hi> (<hi>by the thirty Degrees of Joannes Climmacus</hi>) to this horrible Cliff ſo near a Precipice, to this Maſter-peece of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme Villany? When we <hi>go from vertue to vertue,</hi> we are brought at laſt to a ſublime performance of <hi>heroical</hi> and <hi>eminent vertue.</hi> No man cometh by <hi>ſacred Aſcenſions,</hi> to the Creſt or Spire of unheard of, and almoſt unconceivable villanies. Go ye dirty Hypocrites, ye aſcend in Virtue, according to <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion;</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:118058:8"/> according to <hi>Practice,</hi> ye wrap and ingulph your ſelves into bottomleſs miſchief.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, ye <hi>profeſs</hi> your ſelves to be men of moſt unblamea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble lives; and that as ye are called <hi>religious men,</hi> ſo your <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice</hi> is moſt refined, <hi>Regular,</hi> and religious, your lives are a continual Preſentation to God of the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of <hi>Abram,</hi> as a <hi>Sign</hi> that ye ſhall <hi>inherit the Kingdom of Heaven;</hi> as his <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice</hi> was to him a <hi>Sign,</hi> that he ſhould <hi>inherit the Land of</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan, Gen. 15. 8. <hi>And he ſaid, Lord God, whereby ſhall I know that I ſhall inherit it?</hi> v. 9. <hi>And he ſaid unto him, Take me an Heifer of three years old, and a She-Goat of three years old, and a Ram of three years old, and a Turtle-Dove, and a young Pigeon.</hi> The <hi>Goers on the Ground,</hi> being in their full ſtrength, ſhadow forth your ſtrong Action, and moſt ahle Performance of the <hi>Practical Part:</hi> the <hi>Turtle Dove,</hi> that your whole life is a <hi>mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Penance,</hi> and <hi>continual Martyrdom:</hi> and the <hi>young Pigeon,</hi> the ſweetneſs of your <hi>Innocency</hi> and harmleſneſs. It is not far off, to wit, <hi>v.</hi> 11. <hi>And when the Fowls came down upon the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſes,</hi> Abram <hi>drove them away.</hi> It is viſible, ye are men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of fleſh and blood, and the Devil's Temptations <hi>come down</hi> upon your <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> but they carry not a bill-full away. The Birds fly over your heads, but they do not lodge in your Hair. The <hi>Powers</hi> and <hi>Faculties</hi> that are not in your power, powerfully preſent <hi>idle motions,</hi> but they move you not. Ye wait for another world, and the Apoſtle's <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest expectation of the Creature,</hi> Rom. 8. 19. is in you eſpecially, as the holieſt of earthly <hi>Creatures.</hi> Ye <hi>hold up your heads,</hi> and are ſtretch'd out in moſt <hi>earneſt expectation,</hi> towards the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Chriſt in the Eaſt.</hi> But doe ye hear me, is it clear as Chryſtal, that your <hi>Practical Part</hi> is firm and ſincere?</p>
               <p>By the way as we go. In ſome of your <hi>Religious men, Lucifer</hi> himſelf is predominant. We hear continually and vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, from their own humble Mouths, that they forſooth are of <hi>noble birth,</hi> that their breeding and <hi>Education</hi> was <hi>noble</hi> and dainty, and that now their <hi>Mortification is the greater.</hi> In o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>Aſmodeus</hi> reigns. I could furniſh you with appoſite ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples. And of our <hi>Powder-Traitors</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> had full and plenary poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p>In Chriſtian earneſt, Men whoſe intentions are touch'd with the true loadſtone of Grace, and who purely and piouſly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118058:9"/> ſeek ſolid and <hi>Primitive Perfection,</hi> are not fit Spectators of your Dirtineſſe; your filthineſſe will not endure their Eyes.</p>
               <p>And now, anſwer me ſincerely, Where is the <hi>Turtle Dove</hi> in your Lifes? Ye look ſoberly and whiningly ſometimes, yea gravely in your Houſes, (and ye are moſt ſtately, and require more Courtſhip than the <hi>great Turk,</hi> or <hi>grand Mogul.</hi>) But when ye come into <hi>England,</hi> ye are the merrieſt Men in the Nation, and of all others, moſt given away to Idleneſs, Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and the Follie of the Tavern. And there was, I am cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, no news of the <hi>little Pigeon</hi> in the <hi>Powder-plot,</hi> the great <hi>Powder-plot.</hi> O peerleſs Hypocrites, ye are indeed, after a ſort, as the <hi>Beaſts going on the Ground:</hi> but the <hi>quinteſſential part</hi> of the <hi>Practical part,</hi> and the <hi>Turtle Dove,</hi> and the <hi>young Pigeon</hi> are quite flown away from you. And why did ye not drive away the foul Temptation of the <hi>Powder-plot,</hi> but enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained it, together with the Foul-one himſelf, in your Hearts? And your true and Chriſtian <hi>expectation</hi> of our Lords coming, is yet <hi>expected.</hi> They are your Lives, which torture me. <note place="margin">S. Bern. lib. 2. de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſid. ad Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen.</note> Here is <hi>Sedes prima, &amp; vita ima,</hi> as S. <hi>Bernard to Eugenius; a high place for Meditation, and a baſe low Life, as low as Hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, ye <hi>profeſs,</hi> that ye are men of ſoluble and melting Hearts; and that Donum Lacrymarum, the <hi>Gift of Tears,</hi> is part of your proper Dowry; and that ye weep continually for your own Sins, and for the ſins of the World. Ye avouch, that Chriſt calls unto you eſpecially, Cant. 5. 6. <hi>Open to me, my Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, my love, my dove, my undefiled; for my head is filled with dew, and my locks with the drops of the night.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Chald. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphr.</note> Ye do illuſtrate it out of the <hi>Chaldee:</hi> Capili capitis mei pleni ſunt lacrymis tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is, ſicut Vir cujus capilli capitis tinguntur de rore caeli: et cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinnus caeſariei meae, repletus guttis eſt oculorum tuorum. <hi>The hairs of my head are full of thy tears, as a man whoſe hair is all bedewed and pearl'd with the dew of heaven; and my locks are filled with the drops of thine eys.</hi> And ye give us to learn, that the Prieſts of old times when they <hi>celebrated Maſſe,</hi> were wont to weep whole ſhowrs of tears; and that therefore, they had a Napkin hanging on their left hand: <note place="margin">Amalar. lib 3. de Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticis offic. c. 24.</note> of which <hi>Amalarius.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Venerab. Beda in Collectan. to. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Venerable Bede,</hi> ſpeaking of the <hi>Prieſtly Veſtments,</hi> calls it <hi>map<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pula,</hi> or <hi>amapha;</hi> and he ſayes, that the Prieſt wore it on his left hand. Whence it is undeniable, that this <hi>mappula</hi> was
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118058:9"/> in place of the <hi>manipulus</hi> now worn by the Prieſt on the left arm<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for, <hi>manipulus,</hi> is quaſi manus mappula, <hi>as the hand-napkin:</hi> and the Prieſt putting on the <hi>manipulus,</hi> praies, Merear, Domine, portare manipulum fletus &amp; doloris, ut cum exultatione recipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am mercedem laboris, <hi>Let me, ô Lord, bear the Maniple of Weeping &amp; Grief, that with exultation I may receive the reward of my labor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A word now, pray: Have ye <hi>a fountain of tears in your eyes?</hi> or, is the Head of Chriſt adorned with your tears, as with O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rient Pearls? Have ye wept your eyes dim in the <hi>celebration of the Myſteries?</hi> How comes then, this <hi>Powder-plot?</hi> Is this the <hi>proper Effect</hi> of your tears, and weeping? Have ye in the <hi>cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the Holy Myſteries,</hi> wept your ſelves into a <hi>Powder-plot?</hi> Does your weeping for Sin, produce a ſin above all the ſinnes that ever were heard of? I warrant, ye had great ſtore of the <hi>tears of the Crocodile</hi> ready too, to ſhed over the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Houſe. Go, go, ye are drie and dull Weepers, ye ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wept ſo many tears, as would have quencht this magazin of ſulphur and powder, had it broke forth into effect. Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, now ye have a new reaſon of weeping; weep on, and drown the memory of this moſt loathed and odious Miſchief, if ye are able.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Ye <hi>profeſſe,</hi> that ye are great Lovers of Princes; and that Princes, ordained by your <hi>ſacred Rites,</hi> are <hi>ſacred Perſons.</hi> Indeed, the Princes are they, who chiefly uphold and enrich you. They have multiplied your <hi>Religious Houſes,</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasteries:</hi> they have beautified them. Ye know, that the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> were inſtalled in the pronouncing of theſe words by the <hi>Patriarch, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, be thou holy;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Curiopalus in Hiſt.</note> who like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, in the very pronunciation, did anoint the head of the <hi>Emperour, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, in the form of a Croſſe,</hi> with oil; and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently added, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>be thou worthy;</hi> intimating, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could make him worthy of an <hi>Empire,</hi> but <hi>Holineſs.</hi> And ye know that Kings anointed with oil, are thereby rendred ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of <hi>Spiritual Juriſdiction,</hi> and of the <hi>giving of Benefices,</hi> as in whom there is. Jus Patronatus, the <hi>Right of Patronage.</hi> And ye know again, that Kings are certain foundations of their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; and that they are called Mich. 6. 2. the <hi>ſtrong foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the earth.</hi> And therefore, a King is named in the <hi>Greek Language,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, quòd ſit <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, populi baſis; becauſe he is the <hi>baſis</hi> and <hi>foundation of the people:</hi> And if the <hi>foundation</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:118058:10"/> be ſubverted, all is ruinated. And the <hi>Hebrew word Adon,</hi> from whence comes <hi>Adonai,</hi> ſignifying Dominus, <hi>Lord,</hi> is bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from <hi>Eden,</hi> a <hi>baſis</hi> or <hi>foundation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Me thinks now, that ye having had ſo many Princes your moſt royal Benefactours, might have been loyal, and ſpared your own Prince for their ſakes, with whom your oil and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies ſtill remained; which enſtated him, even in your judgements, holy and inviolable. And me thinks ye ſhould not have adventured to deſtroy the <hi>foundation</hi> of a kingdom; the People, together with the <hi>foundation</hi> on which they ſtood, <hi>root and branch.</hi> I thought, that the hands of the Clergie had been <hi>ſet apart</hi> from all bloud; eſpecially, from the bloud of their lawfull Princes. How can the <hi>bloudy Hands of a Priest,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort with an <hi>unbloudy Sacrifice?</hi> Yee are ſtill Hypocrites, and your <hi>Profeſſion</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> are divers in their Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, ye <hi>profeſs,</hi> that <hi>ye mortifie the luſts of your Bodies;</hi> and that ye act over again, everie day, the ſevere execution of St. <hi>Hilarion</hi> upon his Bodie: <note place="margin">S. Hieron. in vitâ Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larionis.</note> who ſpeaks to his Bodie in St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> Ego te, Aſelle, jam non hordeo, ſed paleis alam, ne calcitres, <hi>O my Body, my Aſſe, I will not feed thee now with bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, but with chaff, leſt being high-fed, thou ſhouldeſt kick.</hi> And the People are diligently taught, that Beaſts were not offered unto God under the <hi>old Law,</hi> until they were dead, and the bloud, which is Paſſionum vehiculum, <hi>the Chariot of the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> was clean run out. Yea, theſe <hi>mortified Men,</hi> are as Cloth before the Tailor, readie to be cut into any faſhion; or, like a dead Corps on the ſhoulders of the Bearers, apt to be carried, without the leaſt repugnance, even whither they will carrie it. They would make us believe, that they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently knowing in Cuſtodia Cordis, &amp; Senſuum; <hi>in the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the Heart, and of the Senſes;</hi> and when they are in their Poſtures, <hi>they will not look beyond the length of a Grave.</hi> They bring Scripture, by a kinde of <hi>material Concurrence,</hi> into their <hi>pious Juggle,</hi> Proverbs 4. 23. <hi>Keep thy Heart with all diligence: for out of it are the iſſues of life.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Edit. Lat. Text. Grae.</note> The <hi>Latin</hi> holdeth up, Omni cuſtodiâ ſerva Cor tuum, <hi>Keep thy Heart with all guard.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Text. Grae.</note> In the <hi>Greek</hi> it runs, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Which word is brought from the Warrs, and ſignifies the keeping of a place with a militarie Guard. And there were
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118058:10"/> in war, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Guards for the ſecuring of ſuch places both by day and night.</hi> Thoſe were by the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> properly called <hi>Excubiae,</hi> theſe <hi>Vigiliae.</hi> Therefore theſe dead-will'd men ſtand cloſe to it, That They keep continual <hi>Guards</hi> over their <hi>Hearts</hi> and <hi>Senſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But had they kept their <hi>Hearts,</hi> they had never entred ſuch a damnable Plot into them. Had they kept a guard upon their own ſenſes, and not <hi>look'd beyond the length of their own Graves,</hi> they had never found the way to the Parliament-Houſe upon ſuch a monſtrous and menſtruous occaſion. O Hypocrites, load not our ears with your <hi>Aſs-bodies,</hi> and your ſacrificed Beaſts, with your <hi>ſimilitudes</hi> of the Tailor and his Cloth; and of the Bearers, bearing the dead Body. Trouble us not with your <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Tell not us of God in your <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> when we ſee with our eyes, <hi>Baalzebub; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the God of corrupting Flies,</hi> and with him a whole <hi>Legion of Devils</hi> in your <hi>Practice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I muſt needs parl here a little with our <hi>Monk.</hi> (And yet, not I, but my <hi>Angel</hi>) If ye <hi>Monks</hi> are ſuch <hi>rigid Mortifiers of your Hearts and Senſes,</hi> how comes it to paſs that the Popiſh Alewife yonder, bedaubs a ſtrict-liv'd Man amongſt you, whom ye have lately ſent to hear the <hi>Confeſſions</hi> of the <hi>Nuns</hi> at <hi>Cambray.</hi> I confeſs, Her Tongue is the fouleſt and filthieſt of all that ever I heard word it; but ſhe is of your own Raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feather, your <hi>practical feather;</hi> and we hear not of her <hi>ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi> Beſides, our <hi>Hamborough</hi>-Merchants report (but I hope they ſpeak it not out of the Tavern) that variety of choice Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, ſtrong Wines, good Beer, and ſpecial <hi>Tobacco</hi> were the greateſt <hi>Mortifications</hi> they ever ſaw at the <hi>Engliſh Monaſtery</hi> in <hi>Lambſpring;</hi> and it is every where known, (ſome ſay, I know it not) that the <hi>Monks</hi> in the <hi>Engliſh Monaſterie</hi> at St. <hi>Mallows,</hi> come ordinarily drunk into the Quire. Theſe are but the fragments or Segments of what I can produce. And all this while your <hi>Procurator for Paris</hi> lies <hi>dormant,</hi> but I ſhall have time to wake him.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, ye <hi>profeſſe,</hi> that ye are always on the wing, always in your high Thoughts and <hi>Meditations.</hi> The <hi>Jeſuits</hi> will ſtuff our ears with the <hi>crambe</hi> of their <hi>Spiritual Exerciſe;</hi> and the <hi>Monks</hi> with their <hi>Meditations,</hi> according to the Rule of St. <hi>Bennet;</hi> and thoſe amongſt the <hi>Bonedictines,</hi> are able to entice the Soul out of the Body: <hi>Meditations</hi> are admirably uſefull,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118058:11"/> and <hi>Scripture</hi> ſets Gods mark upon <hi>Meditations, Cant.</hi> 6. 5. <hi>Thy Hair is as a Flock of Goats.</hi> The <hi>Hairs</hi> of our Head are our Thoughts; and the <hi>Goats</hi> feed always on high places, as on the tops of Rocks and Mountains. But if your Meditations are high, ought they not likewiſe to be pure and harmleſs? The Prophet <hi>David</hi> exalts his voice, and cries, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55. 6. <hi>O that I had wings like a Dove: for then would I flie away, and be at reſt.</hi> He wiſhes not to himſelf, the feet of a Dove, that he may walk upon Dunghils; or the wings of a Hawk or Eagle, that he might purſue others to deſtruction; but only the <hi>wings of a Dove,</hi> a <hi>meditating Creature,</hi> that he might fly to ſome hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den place of <hi>Recollection,</hi> and there meditate. A righteous heart walks in her <hi>Meditation,</hi> ſuper montes aromatum, <hi>upon the Mountains of Spices,</hi> as it is <hi>Cant.</hi> 8. 14. where every ſtep is ſweet, odoriferous, and harmleſs; and ſuch a one dies at laſt like the <hi>Phoenix,</hi> in the delicious odours of a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> life.</p>
               <p>Now in this pious <hi>Meditation,</hi> or <hi>Spiritual Exerciſe,</hi> which <hi>prepared</hi> you, in a <hi>Dark Chamber,</hi> wherein light aſſiſted you no farther, than in the fight of ſome <hi>horrid Picture,</hi> before this high attempt of blowing up the Parliament Houſe: Pray, which was your <hi>Punctum Primum,</hi> firſt point? <hi>Sans</hi> doubt, it was that the <hi>King and his family muſt be extirpated.</hi> But hear a little, was this the <hi>Meditation of the Dove?</hi> Or, were ye then footing it <hi>upon the Mountains of Spices?</hi> O Hypocrites be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all Hypocrites, Strike not our Ears with your <hi>Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> whereof the <hi>Puuctum ultimum,</hi> laſt point, is Fire, Sword, Blood, Maſſacre.</p>
               <p>Eighthly, Ye <hi>profeſſe,</hi> That ye ſing God's Praiſes in the <hi>holy Quire,</hi> day and night. Ye throw abroad, that in this regard, ye are ſtated in the higheſt <hi>Degree of Perfection.</hi> Ye pull home, and apply the two laſt <hi>gradual Pſalms</hi> to your ſelves, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133. 1. <hi>Behold how good and how pleaſant it is for Brethren to dwel to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in unity.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Sept.</note> The <hi>Septuagints</hi> read, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to dwell toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into the ſame thing,</hi> the ſame faith. <note place="margin">St. Hieron.</note> St. <hi>Hierom</hi> gives: Ecce quam bonum, &amp; quam decorum, <hi>Bohold, how good, and how comly,</hi> The <hi>Hebrew word</hi> is nahhim, which ſignifies <hi>fair,</hi> and <hi>comely.</hi> The word nahhim is attributed to the <hi>Bridegroom,</hi> and interpreted <hi>fair;</hi> Cant. 1. 16. <hi>Behold, thou art fair, my beloved:</hi> And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 234. 1. <hi>Behold, bleſs ye the Lord, all ye Servants of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118058:11"/> Lord, which by might ſtand in the houſe of the Lord.</hi> v. 2. <hi>Lift up your hands in the Sanctuary, and bleſs the Lord.</hi> Ye note, that where it is ſaid <hi>Pſ.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>and in his Law doth he meditate day and night:</hi> The <hi>Hebrew word</hi> ſignifying <hi>night,</hi> comes from a <hi>Root,</hi> interpreted, <hi>he howled;</hi> and thence ye raiſe, that ye ſing God's praiſes by <hi>night,</hi> when the Wolves howl, and when wicked men ſing and revel in Taverns, and looſe Houſes, and there wallow in the ſink of all impurity. Yea, this <hi>Quire-Monk</hi> will farther preſs upon us, that in the year of Chriſt 459. in the <hi>Church of Conſtantinople, Gennadius</hi> being Archbiſhop thereof, a <hi>Monaſtery</hi> was erected which they named <hi>Coenobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Acoemetarum, the Monaſtery of thoſe that ſleep not,</hi> from the <hi>Greek</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, who ſang God's praiſes without pauſe, and without end. The Secret is, they were divided into three Quires; and while the one Quire ſang, the other ſlept; and ſo they went the round, and thus repreſented the Singers of Heaven, that ſing God's Praiſes for hereafter in all Eternity. <note place="margin">Drexell. de Eternit. Conſid. 3.</note> They bring in the Rere <hi>Drexellius</hi> a <hi>Jeſuit</hi> for their Author.</p>
               <p>And now ye pretious ſingers of God's praiſes, either by day or night, what kind of praiſes did ye ſing to God in the dark night, when <hi>Guido Faux</hi> held a Guide or Candle to your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren? was it your <hi>good and pleaſant unity,</hi> that was imployed in this moſt horrible <hi>Conſpiracy?</hi> Ye beat into us, that in the end of all your <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Meditations,</hi> ye build, as it were a Sconſe of <hi>good purpoſes.</hi> Did <hi>your lifting up of your hands in Gods Houſe by day or night,</hi> produce this black <hi>purpoſe,</hi> this ugly Monſter of the <hi>Night?</hi> Is this <hi>fair</hi> and <hi>comely,</hi> and like the <hi>Bridegroom?</hi> Can ye be ſo unreaſonable as to think, that any Miſcreant in the whole world was as wickedly buſied that black <hi>night</hi> as your ſelves? And if ye could ſet up all your <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries,</hi> to praiſe God without ſtop or intermiſſion; while ſome of your Brethren, who are not ſo Quire-ſtrong, are let looſe for ſuch horrid imployments, that is, to thunder out Gods praiſes in <hi>Powder-plots;</hi> we ſhall think you as ye are, Superla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Hypocrites; and that, while ye <hi>profeſs</hi> to ſing God's prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, your performance ſings Hymns and Lands to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil.</p>
               <p>Ninethly, Ye <hi>profeſs,</hi> that ye are <hi>Miſſiouers, Apoſtles,</hi> and appointed for the <hi>Converſion</hi> and <hi>Salvation</hi> and Souls. Ye firm it by Scripture, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132. 16. <hi>I will alſo cloth her Prieſts
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118058:12"/> with Salvation.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Paraph. Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d.</note> The <hi>Chaldee</hi> annexeth, veſtibus redemptionis, <hi>with the Garments of Redemption.</hi> Ye make us know, That the <hi>Image of Chriſt,</hi> carrying home the loſt Sheep upon his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, was very antient and famous among you, and that this <hi>figure</hi> was enſtamped upon your <hi>Patens</hi> and <hi>Chalices,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Tert. lib. de Pudic. cap. 4.</note> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> hath left upon Record. <note place="margin">Iſid. Peluſ. lib. 1. Ep. 136.</note> And <hi>Iſidore Peluſiot</hi> hath committed to Poſterity, that the Biſhops were wont to wear a certain <hi>Superhumeral,</hi> called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, made of Wool, and ſignifying <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the skin of the Sheep,</hi> which Chriſt having found, carried home upon his ſhoulders. <note place="margin">Sim. Theſſ. in Biblio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thec. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum.</note> Ye put into our mouths out of <hi>Simeon Theſſalonicenſis,</hi> the very <hi>form of words</hi> which the <hi>Biſhops</hi> uſed in their putting it on. And the <hi>Vertue</hi> attending upon this duty is, in your own ſtile, Zelus Animarum, <hi>the Zeal of Souls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now confeſs ingenuouſly, were ye clothed in this <hi>Powder-Treaſon</hi> with <hi>Sarments of Redemption,</hi> or of <hi>Deſtruction?</hi> Are ye the <hi>Diſciples</hi> of him that carried home the <hi>wandring Sheep,</hi> and reſtored it to the Flock (<hi>O Lord of the whole earth,</hi> thou knoweſ, ſuch Hypocrites are not extant in all the earth) or, of him that devours both Sheep and Flock? Have not ye given the ſcandal unto this Age, which ſome diſſolute and careleſſe <hi>Chriſtians</hi> gave to the <hi>Romans</hi> in the infancy of the Church; who therefore called Chriſt, not <hi>Chriſtum</hi> Chriſt, but <hi>Chre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stum,</hi> quaſi <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, utilem, as <hi>profitable,</hi> becauſe his Name and Religion were very profitable to thoſe his <hi>Profeſſours,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Lamprid. in vitâ A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xandri Severi.</note> as <hi>Lampridius</hi> hath commended to Poſterity. Is this the way of your <hi>Zeal of Souls?</hi> Pſal. 29. 9. <hi>The voice of the Lord maketh the Hindes to Calve.</hi> The Interpretation is, The Hindes doe bring forth with much difficulty: But when it <hi>thunders,</hi> they fear; and then bring forth. And ſo <hi>the voice of God</hi> here, is <hi>Gods thunder in the Clouds.</hi> Theſe heavenly Men found, that the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> did not eaſily bring forth according to their Senſe, and therefore their mind was now, to <hi>thunder</hi> them into a fear and trembling, and ſo, <hi>make the Hindes to Calve.</hi> O Hypocrites, <note place="margin">Mar. 3. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>the Sons of Thunder</hi> did not purchaſe their Name upon this horrid account.</p>
               <p>Tenthly, ye <hi>profeſs.</hi> That ye have <hi>Devotions</hi> and <hi>Aſpirations</hi> tuned and accommodated unto all Times and Places. <note place="margin">Petr. Chryſ. Serm. 9.</note> Ye drop into us, out of <hi>Petrus Chryſologus,</hi> In plateis, &amp; in triviis, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Pietas habet Secretum, <hi>In the Streets, and where ſundry
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118058:12"/> waies meet, Godlineſs hath its Secret.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">S. Hier. Ep. 22. ad Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoch. Virg. Idem ibid.</note> Ye bring to your hive, out of St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> Sanctisetiam ipſe eſt Somnus Oratio, <hi>The very Sleep of the Saints of God is a Prayer.</hi> They lay them down to ſleep with an <hi>Aſpiration,</hi> and it is an <hi>Aſpiration</hi> that wakes them. And again from the ſame Epiſtle, Eſto Cicada nocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, <hi>Be thou the Graſhopper of the night.</hi> Ye give it ſinews from Scripture; As, Cant. 4. 11. <hi>Thy lips, O my Spouſe, drop as the honey-comb: honey and milk are under thy tongue;</hi> That is, Thou haſt moſt ſweet expreſſions of Love, which thy Heart continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſends forth to thy Tongue, by which thou doſt ſweeten the bridegroom to thee: Thou keepeſt both <hi>honey</hi> and <hi>milk</hi> under thy Tongue; thou haſt Leſſons lying alwaies in ambuſh under thy Tongue; and expedited both for the production of <hi>Spiritual nouriſhment</hi> and <hi>Profit,</hi> and of <hi>Pleaſure:</hi> For <hi>profitable nouriſhment,</hi> as <hi>Milk;</hi> for <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> as <hi>Honey.</hi> Theſe are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed to meet and congratulate with all Occaſions, and whatſoever offers it ſelf.</p>
               <p>I beſeech you, anſwer me plainly, What divine <hi>Aſpirations</hi> and <hi>Ejaculations</hi> had ye, wherewith to <hi>ſpiritualize</hi> this moſt <hi>damnable Plot?</hi> What choice Texts of Scripture could <hi>Faux</hi> produce to concurr with his <hi>dark-Lanthorn;</hi> or, with the ſight of the <hi>Cellar</hi> throng'd with Gun-powder and Barrs of Iron? What <hi>Milk</hi> or <hi>Honey</hi> could lie waiting and watching under the Tongues of <hi>Garnet</hi> or <hi>Oldcorn,</hi> to ſalute in the <hi>language of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> this horrible overthrow? or under the tongue of <hi>Tomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> who vaunted at <hi>Rome,</hi> that he digg'd and delv'd under the Parliament-Houſe, beyond the ſweat of his Brows? O Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, ye have proſtituted all the ſweet <hi>Delicates of Devotion,</hi> to the contempt of men, by the moſt wicked Practices that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver humane ears entertained.</p>
               <p>Eleventhly, Ye profeſs, That ye are Perſons of moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>Charity,</hi> and <hi>Humility,</hi> and that yours is the <hi>tried, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, and perfect Faith,</hi> of which <hi>St. Paul,</hi> Galat. 5. 6. <hi>Faith which worketh by love.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Tho. à Kemp. de Imitat. Chriſti, lib. 3. cap. 13.</note> Your <hi>Novice</hi> hears daily from you out of <hi>Thomas à Kempis,</hi> Diſce obtemperare, Pulvis; Diſce te humiliare terra et limus, et ſub omnium pedibus incurvare—, ut omnes ſuper te ambulare poſſint, et ſicut lutum platearum conculcare. <hi>Learn to obey, O thou Duſt; Learn to humble thy ſelf, O thou Earth and mud, and to bow thy ſelf under the feet of all Perſons—, that all men may walk upon thee, and kick thee as the dirt of the Streets.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:118058:13"/>
               <p>The Holy Ghoſt appeared in the form of a <hi>Dove,</hi> and of <hi>Fire.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">S. Aug. Tract. 6. in Ioan.</note> And <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks learnedly to it, Nè Spiritu ſanctificati dolum habeant, in Columbâ demonſtratum eſt: nè Simplicitas frigida remaneat, in igne demonſtratum eſt. <hi>Leſt thoſe who are ſanctified by the Spirit, ſhould have Craft and Deceit,</hi> (without which <hi>Deceit</hi> and <hi>Craft</hi> none are, but ſuch as are <hi>profoundly humble,</hi>) <hi>it is demonſtrated in the Dove: leſt Simplicity ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main cold,</hi> (and without <hi>Charity,</hi>) <hi>it is demonſtrated in the fire.</hi> So that, from your <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Humility,</hi> ye ſtrongly deduce, that ye are of the <hi>Holy Ghost.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now I gently entreat you, Whither was your <hi>Seraphical Charity</hi> gone a Pilgrimage, when this <hi>grand Plot</hi> was on the wheel? And, where in the ground had your <hi>Profound Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> hid it ſelf? Ye were low-minded indeed; for ye dug deep under the <hi>Parliament-Houſe;</hi> and whatſoever the <hi>inflammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> were, wherewith ye were inflamed, ye would have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed thouſands of others, with your new and <hi>strange Fire.</hi> O new <hi>Humility!</hi> O ſtrange <hi>Charity!</hi> And yet ye are in your own Looking-glaſs, the only <hi>humble Souls,</hi> the only <hi>charitable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons;</hi> People out of a <hi>Cloyſter,</hi> are droſs, dirt, dunghil-filth, if ſet in the ſame ballance of compariſon with you. O Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of a deep die!</p>
               <p>Twelfthly, and laſtly; (for, Time checks me,) Ye <hi>profeſs,</hi> That ye come at laſt, even in this world, to be <hi>Gods;</hi> and this, not only in <hi>Power,</hi> as Princes, Judges, &amp;c. but alſo in <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Perfection.</hi> Moreover, That ye grow more and more Gods while ye live. And your invincible reaſon is, Quia nullus eſt Deificationis terminus; <hi>becauſe Deification hath no end.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">S. Dionyſ. Areop. lib. 1. De Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin. Nom.</note> Ye pull to you <hi>Dionyſius Areopagita,</hi> calling thoſe who are ſtudious of <hi>Perfection,</hi> Deiformes, &amp; ſe Deificantes, <hi>Deiform, and Deifying themſelves.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">S. Doroth. Serm. 1.</note> Ye ſend us to St. <hi>Dorotheus, Biſhop of Tyre,</hi> a <hi>Greek Author,</hi> who calls the old Fathers near Chriſt, Deiferos Patres, <hi>Fathers carrying God in and about them.</hi> Ye make it faſt by Argument, Whereas God and Chriſt are propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for our imitation, we are invited, as it were, to an <hi>infinite Perfection.</hi> Texts are cited to appear, 1 Pet. 1. 15. <hi>As he which hath called you, is holy; ſo be ye holy in all manner of converſation.</hi> Matth. 11. 29. <hi>Learn of me, for I am meek and lowly in heart.</hi> Matth. 5. 48. <hi>Be ye therefore perfect, even as your Father which is in heaven is perfect.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:118058:13"/>
               <p>Judge, O ye Angels, and Men; Were theſe <hi>Viri Sangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> Men of Blonds, Gods, or Devils? Did they imitate in this vaſt Sea or Miſchief, <hi>God?</hi> Did they imitate <hi>Jeſus,</hi> a <hi>Saviour?</hi> Were they made <hi>partakers of the divine Nature?</hi> or, were they <hi>Devils incarnate?</hi> Are theſe (O my God!) the <hi>Deiform Saints,</hi> and they who <hi>deify themſelves?</hi> Are theſe, as one ſaith, <hi>Chriſts in the Divinity and Humanity?</hi> O Antichriſtian hypocrites! They profeſs <hi>Chriſt;</hi> they perform <hi>Antichriſt:</hi> They profeſs <hi>God;</hi> they perform the <hi>Devil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I could wade exceedingly further. But by what ye have heard, it is plentifully evinced, that they wondrouſly diſſent from their own <hi>Profeſsion.</hi> And if ye look upon them general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in their other Actions; ye will find their <hi>Lives</hi> to jarr and and quarrel with their <hi>Doctrines.</hi> Their Pens ſpeak one thing, and their hands and hearts another. This Diſcoverie I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to the World.</p>
               <p>Take eſpecial notice, I pray, that the <hi>Powder Treaſon</hi> is pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatly applauded by many, and that nothing is diſliked in it, but the want of ſucceſs; and therefore, theſe Objections are in force, and militant againſt all ſuch, in regard of their <hi>Will of Approbation,</hi> and their Affection to the <hi>Saintſhip</hi> of <hi>Garnet,</hi> and his <hi>holy Medals.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I inferr, firſt, Theſe damnable <hi>Plotters</hi> know not the way of God, Exod. 34. 6. <hi>God is mercifull, and gracious, long-ſuffering, and abundant in goodneſs and truth.</hi> Micah 7. 18. <hi>he delighteth in mercie.</hi> 2 Cor. 1. 3. He is <hi>the Father of mercies.</hi> Theſe Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſſes of Chriſtians, have no mercie. <hi>Prov.</hi> 12. 10. <hi>A righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man regardeth the life of his beaſt: but the tender mercies of the wicked are cruel.</hi> Hence in Scripture, a juſt man is called <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſid,</hi> that is, <hi>pious</hi> and <hi>mercifull:</hi> and <hi>Justice</hi> is called <hi>cheſed,</hi> that is, <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Mercy.</hi> The Reaſon is at hand, Becauſe the <hi>Charity authorized by true Faith,</hi> which acting in the virtue of it, conſtitutes a man <hi>juſt,</hi> conſtitutes him alſo <hi>merciful;</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>proper Work</hi> of <hi>Charity,</hi> to love all, and to do good to all. On the other ſide, A wicked man is void of Charitie, and full of the <hi>love of himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A reaſon, <hi>ab extrinſeco, from without,</hi> why theſe Men are ſo cruel and bloud-thirſtie, may be, becauſe they run often from the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Armie in <hi>Flanders,</hi> to be <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Benedictives;</hi> (ye ſhall know one of them by this Mark: He ſpeaks like a <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifico</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:118058:14"/> concerning <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek,</hi> and hardly underſtands <hi>Latin.</hi>) And ſuch are commonly, Men fram'd and faſhion'd for Crueltie, and Falſhood, and even all the Sinnes of a lewd Camp.</p>
               <p>I inferr, ſecondly, Theſe Hell-inſtructed <hi>Plotters,</hi> know not the way of Chriſt; of whom it is prophecied, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 9. 6. <hi>The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſhall be upon his ſhoulder.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Text. Heb.</note> The <hi>Hebrew,</hi> for <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> gives <hi>Miſra,</hi> being, as the <hi>Hebrew Doctors</hi> teach, a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract of <hi>Miſſir ſara,</hi> Ex ſpinâ Imperium; that is, <hi>The Crown of his Government, ſhall be of Thorns.</hi> He was a King devoted to <hi>Griefs</hi> and <hi>Sorrows;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">See Iſ. 53. 4.</note> and therefore, his Crown was agreeable. And if this King, who wears a Crown of Thorns, be angrie; he does not preſently go a <hi>plotting,</hi> he is quickly pleas'd again. <note place="margin">S. Hil. in Pſal. 2.</note> S. <hi>Hilary</hi> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaks like himſelf, <hi>Virga de radice Jeſſe floruit, ut virgae ſeveritatem floris ſuavitas temperaret; A rod flouriſhed from the root of</hi> Jeſſe, <hi>that the ſweetneſs of the flower ſhould aſſwage the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veritie of the Rod.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe our greedie Suckers of Bloud, are cruel without mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie; and they call their Cruelties, Mercies: <note place="margin">Ammian. Marcell. l. 39.</note> as <hi>Valentinian</hi> the <hi>Emperour</hi> merrily called his She-Bear <hi>Innocency,</hi> which in ſport (but in earneſt) had devour'd manie poor Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</p>
               <p>I inferr, thirdly, Theſe Villanous <hi>Plotters,</hi> know not the way of God's Church. The <hi>Spouſe</hi> ſings of her ſelf, Cant. 5. 5. <hi>My hands dropped with myrrhe, and my fingers with ſweet-ſmelling myrrhe.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Edit. Lat.</note> The <hi>Latin</hi> ſomewhat differs, Manus meae ſtillaverunt myrrham, et digiti mei pleni myrrhâ probatiſſimâ; <hi>My hands dropped with myrrhe, and my fingers were full of moſt approved myrrhe;</hi> that is, of myrrha prima, and electa, the <hi>firſt,</hi> and <hi>cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen myrrhe,</hi> which flows of it ſelf, without cutting and gaſhing the Tree. Myrrhe is an Enemie to <hi>Corruption.</hi> The <hi>Spouſe laies up her Treaſure in Heaven:</hi> and no <hi>corrupted Works</hi> fall from her <hi>ſingers.</hi> Her Actions bring no man to untimely death and <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption;</hi> but her aim is, to carrie all before her to <hi>incorruption</hi> and immortalitie.</p>
               <p>Theſe Ghoſts of the old Chriſtians, have <hi>corrupted hands,</hi> they do not <hi>forgive ſins,</hi> or <hi>abſolve the Penitent</hi> in <hi>Confeſsion,</hi> without <hi>corruption,</hi> without a fee. They reſerve the old phraſe amongſt the Jews, their <hi>hands muſt be filled,</hi> or they ſcarce think themſelves to be <hi>Prieſts,</hi> or their <hi>Ordination valid;</hi> and in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118058:14"/> verity, their <hi>hands</hi> are moreover filled with wild-fire, not with <hi>Myrrhe.</hi> Their chief work is, The perſons which they cannot aſſimilate to themſelves, they will aſſimilate to fire, and convert into miſerable Aſhes.</p>
               <p>I infer, fourthly, This way was worſe than the way of the old Infidels under <hi>Nero.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Tacit. Hiſt. lib. 5.</note> They burnt <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as <hi>Tacitus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, in uſum nocturni luminis, <hi>that they might have light to ſee by night.</hi> Our appointed Victimes of this matchleſs cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, ſhould not have been ſuffered to ſhine by day or by night, but ſhould have been thunder-ſtruck, and torn, yea catch'd away, in a moment of time, as with a whirlwind; and they ſhould not have ſhew'd themſelves in their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>And this way was worſe than the <hi>Sicilian Veſpers,</hi> in which at the Toll of the Bell, the <hi>Frenchmen</hi> were maſſacred. No Bell ſhould have ſounded in the departure of our <hi>Elect Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And truly, the <hi>maſſacre</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> was in no kind to be put into the ballance with this <hi>Machination;</hi> for they ſaw Deſtruction, at ſome diſtance, coming towards them; and a time of <hi>Preparation,</hi> did anſam praebere, hold a <hi>Cup of bleſſing, with the handle towards them.</hi> It was obſtinately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied here, by theſe <hi>Holy Ghoſtly Fathers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And is not all this, founded and grounded upon the curſed <hi>Poſition</hi> of the <hi>Donatiſts?</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">S. Aug. Ep. 48. contra Vincent. Donatist.</note> of the which, St. <hi>Austin,</hi> Quod volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ſanctum eſt, <hi>That which we will have done, is holy, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I infer, fiftly, This is the <hi>malignant way,</hi> and theſe are the true <hi>Malignants; Malignus,</hi> or, a Man of a <hi>malign Heart,</hi> is he, that is male ignitus, <hi>inſpired with an ill fire;</hi> and therefore, is ready to <hi>blow up</hi> all, and to mingle Heaven and Earth. <note place="margin">Ruffin. in Pſal. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Ruffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> is of this judgement, <hi>Malignus,</hi> ſaith he, quaſi malo igne plenus dicitur. <hi>A Malignant is he that is full of evil Fire.</hi> This is the <hi>Malignant Spirit,</hi> that, like fire, cannot reſt, until every <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bustible matter</hi> be conſumed. Theſe are truly the <hi>Children of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial,</hi> as the word is gathered from <hi>beli ol,</hi> that is, ſine jugo, <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out yoke:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">S. Hieron<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> So, many times, S. <hi>Hierom</hi> turns it; and with him, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quila.</hi> They are like the <hi>Wild Boar of the Forrest.</hi> No force can impale them. They break, burn, <hi>blow up all</hi> Barrs, Yokes, Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>Civil, Eccleſiastical, Divine,</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi> of <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:118058:15"/>
               <p>I infer, laſtly, That theſe black Saints, having gone in the Devils high way, may juſtly partake of the Devils Titles.</p>
               <p>Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, when we have look'd every way, and put all our Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities upon the queſt, the Names of <hi>Serpent</hi> and <hi>Dragon,</hi> are their proper Names, the Names that are moſt proportionable to their Nature: becauſe theſe Names moſt comply with the Devil, whoſe (give the word a paſs) <hi>natural Children</hi> they are; and becauſe they denote their crooked and uneven motions, turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and <hi>windings,</hi> which produce more <hi>indirect Angles,</hi> than ever <hi>Euclid</hi> or <hi>Geometry</hi> took notice of.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Sozom. lib. 3. cap. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Sozomenus</hi> commits to our Thoughts concerning <hi>Pachomius</hi> the <hi>Abbot,</hi> that he was the head of a thouſand and three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Monks;</hi> whom that he might the better diſtinguiſh and govern, he divided into four and twenty <hi>Claſses;</hi> according to the number of the Letters in the <hi>Greek Alphabet;</hi> ſo far forth, that in what Letter ſoever they were placed, their Natures and Manners ſhould be deciphered and repre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed by the ſhape of the Letter. Thoſe whom Nature had endowed with a direct and ſimple Diſpoſition (for in thoſe times there were many ſuch) he put into the <hi>Claſſis</hi> of Iota, and they bore that Name. Now is the plaineſt and ſimpleſt Letter of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; it being but <hi>one right little line ſtruck downwards.</hi> But his involv'd, cunning, and obſcure-hearted <hi>Monks,</hi> if leſs cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, he called ζ, if more ξ, becauſe theſe are <hi>Serpentine, Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniſh,</hi> and <hi>winding</hi> Letters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verily-Verily</hi> (they are our Saviours holy Words) I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw (I would I could ſay the contrary) an <hi>Iota Jeſuit</hi> or <hi>Monk</hi> in all my life, but of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Monks</hi> I have ſeen whole ſwarms, being people of dark and crooked Hearts, and of tongues having all <hi>irregular motions,</hi> and moving through every dark place in the whole Labyrinth of a Lye.</p>
               <p>Allow me freedom a little. I know a <hi>Yorkſhire Knight.</hi> Miſtake me not, He is no <hi>Monk,</hi> but his Brother is their <hi>Lord Prelate</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> (for ſuch they prefer, beyond the Seas, who are allied to rich perſons in <hi>England</hi>) and there governs (ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would ſay a naſty crew, I may not, I dare not, I will not) a few <hi>Monks</hi> whom he multiplies with his own poor kinred; yea, there he ſells ſtrong drink to the <hi>drunken Germans.</hi> The <hi>Knight</hi> will tell you in his <hi>York-ſhire Language,</hi> that he has been a <hi>Pilgrim</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and that there he thruſt his right arm,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118058:15"/> even up to his ſhoulder, into the hole on the top of <hi>Mount Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vary,</hi> wherein the <hi>Croſs of our Saviour</hi> was faſtned. My ſcope is, This Arm, notwithſtanding it was ſtraight in the ground, where the <hi>foot</hi> of our <hi>Saviours Croſs</hi> ſtood, turns and <hi>winds</hi> it ſelf in the world, and has more ſtrange <hi>motions</hi> of the <hi>Serpent</hi> in the buſineſs of gain and lucre, than any other Arm in <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> yea of thoſe that never were enquiring into the hole at <hi>Mount Calvary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Their Arms will <hi>winde</hi> and turn, their Hands, their Tongues, their Hearts. Theſe great <hi>Profeſſors</hi> without performance are, as they are call'd, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 5. Natio prava &amp; perverſa, <hi>a crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and perverſe Nation;</hi> and belong to the <hi>crooked Serpent,</hi> Job 26. 13.</p>
               <p>To ſhut up this Note. <note place="margin">Nieremb. Hiſt. Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae, lib. 6. c. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Nierem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ergius</hi> writes of a <hi>ſtinking beaſt</hi> in <hi>India,</hi> the excrement of which is living Snakes. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect, at your leiſure, upon a <hi>Paſſage</hi> in <hi>Geffrey Chaucer;</hi> unto which I adde my grain; If that <hi>stinking Beaſt</hi> the Devil, were in a condition of exerciſing <hi>vital operations,</hi> that is, the <hi>acts of life,</hi> I will not ſay, in his old ſhape of a <hi>Serpent,</hi> but as a <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon,</hi> he could not <hi>analogically</hi> and agreeably have other Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than an <hi>Engliſh Jeſuit,</hi> or (my Heart bleeds Tears) <hi>Monk;</hi> they, are ſo Dragoniſh, ſo fiery, ſo full of new ſhapes, ſo lying, ſo like the Devil.</p>
               <p>I am now yours, Beloved. Firſt, think with your ſelves; Had this Prodigie of miſchief march'd on, and caught effect; as in the death of the little Infants <note place="margin">St. Cyprian. Ep. 24.</note> (for, as St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> takes into Conſideration, Infantia innocens ob nomen ejus occiſa eſt, <hi>Innocent Infancy was fitly killed for his Name.</hi>) As, I ſay, in the death of the little Infants, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2. 18. Rachel <hi>wept for her Children, and would not be comforted, becauſe they were not:</hi> How many <hi>Rachels</hi> ſhould we have had weeping amongſt us? <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel</hi> in the <hi>Oriental Tongues</hi> ſignifies a <hi>Sheep,</hi> and ſhe mighr well weep for her little <hi>Lambs,</hi> cruelly ſlain in rhe cauſe of the <hi>Lamb of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Beloved, Let me commend unto you, the Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of St. <hi>John</hi> (who as he was the <hi>beloved Diſciple,</hi> moſt and chiefly exhorted his <hi>Diſciples</hi> to <hi>Love</hi>) 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 3. 18. <hi>My little Children, let us not love in Word, neither in tongue, but in deed, and in truth. Little Children</hi> love ſincerely, <note place="margin">Mat. 18. v. 2. 4.</note> and therefore our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſet one in the midd'ſt of his Diſciples, exhorting them
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118058:16"/> to be as that little Child. The <hi>Word</hi> is here diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>Tongue.</hi> An <hi>unprofitable word</hi> may perhaps break looſe for want of <hi>continual attention;</hi> but he that gives over the <hi>iuſtrument of Speceh,</hi> which is the <hi>Tongue,</hi> unto <hi>Fraud</hi> and <hi>falſhood,</hi> is himſelf altogether unprofitable. If ye cannot love <hi>ſpiritually, love morally.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139. 4. <hi>There is not a word in my Tongue.</hi> Others ſet it forth. Non eſt dolus in linguâ meâ, <hi>There is no deceit in my Tongue.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">S. <hi>Chryſoſt. in hunc lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</hi>
                  </note> Or, as another in St. <hi>Chryſostom,</hi> Non eſt <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>there is not another and another Speech;</hi> there is no Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betwixt my mind and my Mouth; I concentre my Heart and my Countenance in my Tongue.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Beloved, Ye will hear all this <hi>Powder-Plot</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted by them, and thrown back upon thoſe who then wore the Names of <hi>Puritans.</hi> This, as other Things of the ſame badge, makes evidently plain, that as it is, <hi>Jo.</hi> 8. 44. <hi>They are of their Father the Devil, and that the luſts of their Father they will doe: he was a lyer and a murderer from the beginning,</hi> They are <hi>Lyars, Slanderers, &amp;c.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Plin. nat. hiſt. lib. 8. cap. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Pliny</hi> ſpeaks truly, Nullum tam im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudens Mendacium eſt, ut Teſte careat, <hi>There is not a lye ſo impudent, but it is furniſhed with a witneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now do I greatly want <hi>Raphael Urbinus,</hi> an <hi>Italian Painter,</hi> who having pictured St <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> with red faces, and being demanded the reaſon by a <hi>Cardinal</hi> his noble Cuſtomer, anſwered, That he pictured them, as now they were in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, mainly bluſhing in the ſight of their <hi>wicked Succeſſours.</hi> I would have St. <hi>Ignatius Loiola</hi> painted with a very red face, a face as red as fire; and (be not offended if I modeſtly uſe thy name in the cauſe of Eternity) St. <hi>Bennet</hi> with a face red be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond fire, and as if he had been even now (O ſad News!) plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully entertained at <hi>Lamb spring,</hi> where his <hi>Monks</hi> ſell Beer that paints a deep red in the faces of the <hi>merry Germans.</hi> Now I have ſaid this, I am ſorry; I have a relenting heart beyond Decency.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Beloved, Let us heartily bleſs God, that hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered us. There is, Laus Mentis, Laus Oris, Laus Operis, <hi>the praiſe of Mind, the praiſe of Mouth, the praiſe of Work.</hi> Let us praiſe him chiefly, with our utmoſt praiſe; that is, with holy lives and Converſations.</p>
               <p>For Mouth-praiſes: God's praiſes in <hi>Iob</hi> are excellently co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>incident
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118058:16"/> with our Deliverances, Job 5. 12. <hi>He diſappointeth the Devices of the Crafty, ſo that their Hands cannot perform their Enterpriſe,</hi> v. 13. <hi>He taketh the wiſe in their own Craftineſs, and the counſel of the froward is carried headlong.</hi> And ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Eastern Christians</hi> uſe a verie pious manner of <hi>Salutation</hi> betwixt <hi>Eaſter</hi> and <hi>Whitſuntide.</hi> One meeting an other, ſaith, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Our Lord is riſen.</hi> The other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>it is true<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he is riſen.</hi> He that began, replieth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>he liveth and reigneth for ever and ever.</hi> It were pure Devotion, if for ſome daies after the Celebration of this Deliverance, we did ſalute in our meetings, one the other, after ſome remarkable <hi>Form:</hi> wherin we might join Spirit to Spirit, as in a <hi>holy Kiſſe:</hi> As thus, One ſhould begin, <hi>By the Goodneſs and Mercy of God we were delivered;</hi> The other might anſwer, <hi>It is true, By the Goodneſs and Mercy of God, and by thoſe alone.</hi> And then the firſt again, <hi>We are as men riſen from the grave:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>and if we be riſen with Christ, let us ſeek thoſe things which are above.</hi> And the other might conclude, <hi>It is moſt juſt, that God ſhould live and reign in us, to him be glorie for ever and ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Finally, Beloved, It is a good <hi>Mark</hi> when we are afflicted. The <hi>Hebrew Divines</hi> obſerve, That <hi>Jona,</hi> ſignifying a <hi>Dove,</hi> is ſo called from <hi>Janah,</hi> which is latin'd afflixit, moerore affecit, <hi>he hath afflicted, he hath griev'd,</hi> Becauſe the Dove is perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Hawks, and other Birds of Prey, Pſal. 34. 19. <hi>Many are the afflictions of the righteous; but the Lord delivereth him out of them all.</hi> God make you <hi>righteous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do aſſure you, It is my Glorie, that I bear in my face, a <hi>Mark</hi> of <hi>barbarous cruelty,</hi> given by one linag'd from ſuch like <hi>Saints,</hi> with an <hi>Iriſh Dagger;</hi> and this, <hi>in the maintenance and Defence of Vertue, and Reprehenſion of Vice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let me ſend forth one ſigh, and a groan after it, <hi>O that unwiſe Ewe, and ignorant of future Things, that gave ſuck to the forſaken whelps of the Wolf; which afterwards would have destroyed her, and her young, and all the Flock!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One word more: I ſeldom ſee a <hi>Jeſuitical</hi> or <hi>Monkiſh Good-Man</hi> (ſo they are called) but methinks I behold a ſtately Swan in his ſwimming. The ſwimming Swan ſhews his white fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; but he hides his black leggs under the water. Take the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118058:17"/> Swan from his ſwimming, and ye will quickly perceive his black Walkings.</p>
               <p>Go now, O ye <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> to produce and print ſeveral ſhapes of <hi>Garnet's Straw</hi> (which I have ſeen:) All your ſhapes, and all the ſhapes of the Straw, are not wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h one poor untainted Straw, that has the ſhape wherein God made it.</p>
               <p>A Word now to you, as ye are a <hi>Companie.</hi> That ye, if ye <hi>concurr with the end of your Vocation,</hi> are great Inſtruments of the Advancement of God's Glorie, and of Learning, is a Truth plain to the Eie of Reaſon; but what it is to <hi>concurr with the end of your Vocation,</hi> is not eaſily diſcernable. Therefore, to <hi>concur with the End of your Vocation,</hi> is, to Print and advance <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Truths</hi> and <hi>true Learning,</hi> by the which only, God is glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified. For, if ye walk otherwiſe, ye advance God's diſhonour, and are Enemies to ſound and true Learning: and ye print <hi>Garnet's Straw</hi> in ſeveral ſhapes.</p>
               <p>Ye are the Conduit-Pipes, and Chanels, by the which, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is conveyed to the World: But ye are reaſonable Conduit-Pipes, and Chanels, no ſenſeleſs, and <hi>inanimate;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, be ye ſure and ſecure, that the Water be not foul and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious. As the <hi>Caſe,</hi> and the Die of Chance falls now, It is your Dutie to know the <hi>Subjects of the Diſcourſes</hi> which ye Print; and Ignorantia non excuſat hominem in his quae per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent ad Officium ejus, <hi>Ignorance doth not excuſe a man in the Things which pertain to his Office or Dutie.</hi> Indeed, when that <hi>Office</hi> was an others, who might act at Pleaſure, there was a <hi>large difference.</hi> Give me leave to ſpeak the Words of my own Dutie.</p>
               <p>One Thing more, Becauſe Learning is ſo deeply concern'd in your <hi>Vocation;</hi> ye more comply and are more congruous with your <hi>Vocation</hi> that have received ſome tincture of Learning. Learning is helpfull to all Chriſtians; eſpecially to thoſe, into whoſe <hi>Vocation</hi> it falls.</p>
               <p>We read, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71. in the end of the fifteenth Verſe, and in the beginning of the ſixteenth, <hi>I know not the numbers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; I will go in the ſtrength of the Lord God.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Edit. Vulg.</note> The <hi>Vulgar Latin</hi> clothes it; Quoniam non cognovi literaturam, introibo in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentias Domini: <hi>Becauſe I have not known Learning, I will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the powers of God;</hi> as if they had more of the <hi>Power of God,</hi> and drew nearer to him, that are ignorant of <hi>Learning.</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:118058:17"/>
                  <note place="margin">Sept.</note> The <hi>Septuagint</hi> gives us alſo, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Learning.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Text. Heb.</note> The <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew word</hi> is <hi>Siphrot;</hi> and ſignifies <hi>Ciphers, numbers.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Sym. Rabbini. Arnob. S. Chryſoſt. S. Aug. in Pſal. 71.</note> Thus <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machus</hi> tranſlates it; thus the <hi>Rabbins:</hi> to whom <hi>Arnobius, St. Chryſoſtom,</hi> and <hi>St. Austin</hi> do fully and freely conſent; who take the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>negotiation,</hi> or <hi>merchandizing;</hi> or, if ye will <hi>pragmatizing:</hi> which indeed, throngs a man with temporal buſineſs, and diverts him from knowing the <hi>Works</hi> and <hi>Wonders of Gods ower;</hi> when true Learning enables him to a further Compliance with <hi>divine Power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhut up all, in the Commendation of one ſerious Matter to you. I have not anie Thing of this Orb or Nature, more fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to commend to you, in the Publiſhing of which, ye may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the <hi>Wonders of God's Power;</hi> than ſuch Matters as declare the <hi>Goodneſs</hi> and <hi>Power of God,</hi> in the blazoning of this moſt <hi>horrible Plot<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d of the Diſcoverie attending upon it.</p>
               <p>It is clear, That as a Flower may be painted with it's own colour, and ſurvive it ſelf; ſo this moſt horrid Wickedneſs hath black enough in it ſelf, wherewith to be painted in it's own foul hue. But the Tongues and Pens of Scholars are alſo needfull, as the skilfull hand of the Painter; that it may be tranſlated, in it's own Colour, from Age to Age, from Day to Day, untill we come to the <hi>black Day,</hi> (which the <hi>Plotters</hi> would have repreſented amongſt us) the <hi>Day of Doom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as the Children, and Common People, were taught in the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> commonly to ſing and ſay, <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lujah, Praiſe ye Jah, or God who is:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">St. Hieron. Ep. ad Lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, &amp; ad Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellam.</note> So let it be in uſe with us. And let the Reaſon follow with a Train: For he hath delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red us from the Devil, and the <hi>Engliſh Jeſuits,</hi> and —, (I will here loſe the Word that ſhould follow) that curſed Rabble which <hi>blows up</hi> all; in this our bleſſed Deliverance from the <hi>Powder-Treaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have here eatneſtly defended thoſe whom God hath <hi>won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully delivered:</hi> and in effect, I have defended God and his <hi>wonderfull Deliverance.</hi> I have been vehement againſt wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and wicked Perſons, whereſoever I found them: So was <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and all the <hi>Fathers.</hi> I have inveighed againſt <hi>unprieſtly Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>irreligious religious Men:</hi> Thus did St. <hi>Auſtin, Salvianus, Gildas,</hi> and Armies of others. Ma-Many will haſtily let fly their uneven Cenſures concerning the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118058:18"/> ground of my Quarrel againſt the <hi>Monks;</hi> Aſſuredly, it is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yea more intricate and <hi>winding</hi> than to be comprized pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently by an ordinary Fancy: but I may be able to expreſs it hereafter. Let it ſuffice here, that one Action, wherein they and their envenom'd Friends were buſie Bees and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitors; was more than a <hi>Powder-Plot</hi> againſt me, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that which the <hi>Law of God, of Nature,</hi> and of <hi>Nations</hi> call'd mine, until they came with their Volumus &amp; Jubemus, <hi>we Will and Command.</hi>
               </p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>Laus Deo Liberatori.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Praiſe be unto God o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> Deliverer.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
